[Music]
so
good evening and good day everybody
great to be back with you guys
so today is a live chat session and
before we begin i have an announcement
uh super chats are gone i have decided
to turn off the super chat feature
and the reason for that is that it kind
of creates a divide between the
viewers which i don't think is
appropriate and it's actually unfair to
the
youngsters who can't afford to pay and
it's distracting for me to
see all the colored questions and
it kind of detracts the attention away
from the other questions
so i want all questions to be at the to
to have the same weightage i want to
answer the best questions
so that's the reason why i have decided
to turn off the super chats
uh so thank you to everybody who has
contributed in the past but
going forward super chats will not be
available super stickers are still
available
and super chats will be turned off in
question and answer
sessions maybe in some other future live
episodes we may have it on
i will decide later on and for those of
you who have expressed
a desire to contribute to this work that
i'm doing
i will soon be opening a membership
section
maybe next week or so so i will let you
guys know about it
but it's entirely voluntary and it's
it's not
required that you become a member i will
always answer
all of your questions for free here i
believe that knowledge
should always be free i'm not doing this
for money it's not about the money it's
about
i do this because i enjoy uh having this
conversation with you and enjoy sharing
the knowledge
so knowledge should always be free and
it will always be free here on this
channel
so that's the uh so the channel is
evolving
it's going to evolve further next week
and i will let you know by the end of
this week
so so that's the thing super chats are
gone super stickers are still there and
memberships will be coming within a week
or so
all right so let's get into it i'm gonna
answer your live questions today only
live
and we'll keep it fast we'll keep it
brief
and let me take a look at what questions
you have been
asking question one meghna
asks how did lord macaulay
convince indian leaders that western
education system was better than
gurukuls
and how were the gurus banned he did not
have to convince anybody of anything
right the british were in power and they
used the power and they changed the
system
and they made things such that in order
to get
a job in the indian government the
british indian government
you had to pass through the education
system their british
foreign macaulay and education system so
they constructed
the system of governance and
of of jobs in such a manner that it
became
impossible to get a government job
unless you went through the macaulay
education system so that's why over time
indians had no option but to go through
that and that's the same system we have
today
the education system today is only
geared towards
i mean towards becoming ready for the
job market it doesn't really educate you
so that's the short answer he did not
have to convince anybody he just imposed
it
the british simply imposed this new
education system on the country
and the country was forced to
go along with with the with the program
that they had created
that's in brief i think we should have a
session
separately for education which is a very
important topic so maybe we'll do it
soon
so but in short that's the answer to
your question he did not convince
anybody he just
shoved it down india's throat
okay arindam asks did the neanderthals
procreate with the homo sapiens yes they
did
we have evidence that the neanderthals
procreated with homo sapiens and the
demi servants as well
and it is well known that most
non-african people
all non-african people have about four
to six percent neanderthal dna
so in effect the neanderthals never
vanished they did not actually go
extinct
they live on through us we have
some neanderthal ancestry it's like
having about
i don't know one great great grandparent
or so who's named
something like that so we all have some
neanderthal
ancestry and this is about non-african
humans
so this happened after the out of africa
movement
of our ancestors and they
interbred with the neanderthals probably
somewhere in the middle east
or thereabouts before they moved on to
india and they made india their home
base
from where they went all over the world
and it is also known that some africans
also have a little bit of neanderthal
industry because
probably that what happened was that
some homo sapiens went back into africa
at some point in time
that's what it looks like so human
history
is quite complicated it's not a linear
progression
from homo habilis to homo erectus or
whatever the sequence is
and onwards to homo neanderthales homo
sapiens etc
it's a complex back and forth movement
there are many species and subspecies
some went extinct some are still around
we we have ancestry from various
lineages some of them are not even known
which what they were so it's a complex
uh
scenario the more we under the more
evidence
and data they find the more complex the
story becomes
so it's not a simple linear progression
it's it's much more complex there are
many back and forth movements
there are many ways of migrations
outwards and inwards
so the story is just beginning it's
going to get much more complex
so in short to answer your question yes
the neanderthals did procreate
with our distant ancestors
and they live on through us
okay some more questions some of them
i've already answered i am putting up
short clips
and a few clips per day right now more
later less
so hopefully you will get all the
answers in the short clips the ones
you're seeking
but let me quickly find some more
questions
okay om patak asks how to make a career
in history and mythology as i am deeply
interested in it
right now right from when i was 6 years
old today i am 17
well i'm glad to know that you want to
do that in
india the only career in history and
mythology there's no career in mythology
there's only a career in history and the
only
uh long term path as of today is that of
a history teacher or professor
so you have to either be a history
teacher in a school or a history
professor in a college or a university
there is no research
being done in history so as of today
the only career is that that's the only
career path open to you
in the future maybe if the government
actually starts investing in
real research real research history
research
then we may have history institutes and
those things in the in the future
in which case your career paths could
broaden up
so what i would say right now is
if that's what what you want to do if
being a history teacher interests you
or professor then maybe you can go along
the path
otherwise you can go along with some
other career and keep this option open
because at the age of 17 we don't really
know what we want to do we've all been
there
right i the thing is this if you want to
contribute to the country in some way
then explore different things and try
different job parts
because very soon the job market is
going to be completely transformed
it's all going to be based on skills and
not on your paper degrees
degrees are very soon going to become
irrelevant and obsolete
the education system is already obsolete
so right now we are already seeing this
there's a great demand for skills that
are not taught in our education system
search engine optimization graphic
design website design
website development uh video editing
and so much more there is these are all
skills right these are all artistic
and technical skills and these are very
very valuable you can have a very good
lucrative career based on that
so i would suggest to everybody who's at
this stage 17 16 15 years old
but do go through the education system
just in case because it's always better
to have
two plans plan a plan b so get your
degree whatever you're pursuing
but also learn some skills because it is
in the long term that these skills are
going to be more
valuable and try and build something try
and solve
some problems with these skills because
problem solving is the
rule it's the it's the uh core
uh it's the core of entrepreneurship
so try and learn different skills try
and understand finance try and
understand business
and acquire skills and keep your
passions alive like the this passion in
history and mythology
so if you were to follow this sort of
path and acquire different skills and
also
keep learning the history mythology etc
then maybe 10 years in the future you
will have lots of avenues open to you
in this very field so i would say at
this age don't set yourself
on one single career path keep options
open
keep your passion alive keep nurturing
it and by the time you're 30
you have much better grounding and
understanding of what you want to do
because i think that until the age of 30
we are still
lost and clueless because it takes some
experience to
to reach that understanding of where you
want to be in life
and 30 is very young so you have another
13 years
i would say to explore so try different
jobs try different career paths
and learn as many skills as you can and
maybe by the time you're
about a decade from now you will have a
better idea
of what career paths are open because
the things because
our country and the world will have
changed a lot in the next 10 years
and many many avenues will be open so
that's my
answer to you sir thank you for this
question
arena asks what was the religion of the
questions before they arrived in india
were the hindus or buddhists
i believe that to the skip the kushans
are essentially the easternmost
branch of the skittions that's what they
were they were an
indian origin people this kitchens two
were an indian origin people
the kushans looked more european
than indian i mean if you see the
mummies from the daring basin river
you will see that they they many of them
have have red hair
some of them have blonde hair so it
looks like
they looked more european than indian
but the genetics
were very much indian r1a1a that is the
particular indian lineage you find in
almost all
tariffs and mummies and these are
believed to be
most likely the ancestors of the
questions
so these are essentially an extension of
the skittion peoples these
nomadic peoples who uh prospered across
eurasia all the way from eastern europe
to present day so called xinjiang of
china in the
river basin so it is recorded by the
greeks and by the
uh persians and other peoples that um
this kitchens worshiped the sun
the sun was their god the sun god at
least the primary god i'm sure they were
all
polytheistic like all indian origin
people in the in
in antiquity and what
exactly the religions we don't have
religions
religion is a western abrahamic concept
a religion is something that has one
prophet and one book
and one set of rules that everybody must
follow in
polytheistic cultures
there is no one path to follow you can
follow any path you like essentially
there is there are certain things that
are that have more primacy
but within that or even outside that you
can follow any path you want
so there is no religion as such hinduism
is not a religion it's a culture it's a
civilization
it's it's the essence of a civilization
so we don't know what exactly what
precisely they followed
but they were able the questions they
were able to assimilate
most harmoniously with the larger indian
population
today we don't even know who has koshan
ancestry who is not we all look the same
we all have the same genetics
because they also have the same genetics
as us so
because they were able to integrate so
peacefully so harmoniously with indian
society
it is most likely that they were just as
polytheistic as us
as our ancestors 2000 years ago and they
most likely had the same gods
because in this region of the tariq
basin river
you find lots of carvings and frescoes
and all that
full of indian divinities in art you
know whether buddhist
or whether what we now call hinduism
it's all the same thing actually
like i have explained in the past so
we don't have exact uh data but
from the evidence that we have it is
very clear that these were polytheistic
people and they were very much
the same culture as the indians because
they assimilated so harmoniously without
a single issue at all there is no one
record
of any ethnic strife or cultural strife
or religious strife
any riots any any such thing between
them and the indian people so most
likely they were just as
hindu as our ancestors in mainland india
okay this is a great question abhijit
bose asks why did genghis khan
attack the bombing and buddhas in 12
no sir who told you that he attacked the
bahamian buddhas
he's a guy who built buddhist temples in
quran
in present-day persia and central asia
on the top of this
the uh mosques that he destroyed
right the mongols are known to have done
that
they they they were very respectful
towards the buddha
during chinese khan's time they were
still not officially buddhists
buddhism was present in mongolia they
were very much aware of buddhism
of the teachings of the buddha chinese
himself was a tengrist he believed in
tangirism
that was the culture or practice that he
followed
it is a polytheistic practice which is
very strikingly similar
to vedic hinduism in many ways the
pantheon of gods is almost the same with
different names
and therefore i i mean therefore he
would
he was somebody who respected the buddha
we we know from his actions
so no chinese khan did not attack the
bamiyan buddhas it was the taliban
about 25 30 years ago 25 or so years ago
in the late 90s i think if i'm not
mistaken
they are the ones who attacked the
bombing and buddhas and they are the
ones who blew them up with dynamite
and before the taliban it was aurangzeb
who tried to destroy them with cannons
and he failed so he fired cannons or
at the bomb and buddhas but he was not
able to destroy them he was able to
damage the the statues to some extent
but ching is khan has never attacked any
dharmic faith
any dharmic practice he actually did
did what he could to a certain extent
to strengthen it so this is uh i'm
afraid sir i don't know where you found
this but
it is it is not consistent with the
facts
all right uh
deva bharata asks how can a team evolve
in our indian education system
so i kind of answered that question
again earlier but uh
see right now if you want a job in the
indian job market
you're gonna have to have a degree so
you have to get your degree as of today
maybe 10 years from today it will be
obsolete but as of today
if you're a teen you should get
the degree you should go through the
system whether you like it or not it's a
pointless system
but it's the only one that allows you to
get a job although if you don't have a
degree
you may not not get a job in any big
corporation or any
thing so get a job get a degree get a
job
but also educate yourself outside of the
education
system see the education system prepares
us to
it prepares us for a life of being sheep
it prepares us for this uh
it mentally conditions us towards being
in a state where we are always
obedient always receptive to commands
we don't ask questions and all that it
prepares us for being sheep
so i would say that and it try the
education system tries to take up all of
your time
from the time you're a kid there's so
much homework there's so much
extracurricular activities
that you don't have the time to go on
and play so from a
very early age it kind of tries to
brainwash children
and destroy their creativity and and
talent and inquisitiveness and all of
that
and curiosity so i would say that you
need to take
time out of education to get some real
education
so try to find out what you're
interested in what your passions are
what
what fields or what what questions uh
interest you and try and learn something
outside of the education system today
all the answers are available for free
on the internet just use the power of
whatever your favorite search engine is
and try and learn things and like i said
earlier try and learn some
some skills so many skills are available
you can learn them for free
web design web development graphic
design
photoshop adobe premiere pro and so much
more
search engine optimization these are
very interesting fields actually
and uh it's not hard to learn this stuff
so try and acquire skills
and try and be the best person you can
try and be the try and maximize your
potential
whatever you need to us you need to take
some time to understand
yourself what are your aptitudes what
things are you good at
what things do you like what things
interest you and try and fulfill
try and maximize your potential in these
things and 10 years from now
the skills that you acquire are going to
make you very valuable
not just in the sense of the job market
but a valuable
person for the nation for the
civilization long term
so try and try and develop yourself the
best of your ability
outside of the education system get your
degree
because that's what you need right now
for getting a job but also develop
yourself outside the system
and try and be the best possible person
you can because india
yeah india needs young people who have
this uh
self-confidence and who have these
leadership qualities
so not everybody should be a leader not
everybody is designed
or or or has the opportunity to be a
leader but if you
invest in yourself in this manner if you
have leadership qualities these will
come out
and that's what india needs in the
future we need entrepreneurs we need
leaders we need people with different
talents and skills
so that's what india's young people need
to do today
to invest in themselves today so that
you can give back something to the
country
10 20 years in the future so that's what
we need to do sir
manish asks how can we could get at
physics numerical
to get good at physics first of all you
need to learn math lot of math
and you need to do a lot of practice
solving problems
to learn any skill you don't learn the
skill by reading books you learn the
skill by actually
getting your hands dirty and solving
problems so solve lots of math problems
solve a lot of physics problems and
that's how you get good at physics
that's how you
internalize the laws of physics simple
straight answer
okay what would have happened if there
was no invasion
of the mughals and the british well
india would have been a very different
country
india would still have its original
culture in india
would be still indian today if you see
uh
if you see the sports
when you have a sports event at the
beginning you have this parade or march
past in which everybody dresses up in
the
in the in the national dress of their
country right
so when this happens you will find that
the eastern asian countries
thailand burma cambodia etc
even indonesia they the dresses they
wear
and the culture they demonstrate the
display is more
indian than what the indian contingent
is demonstrating right what the kind of
clothes they're wearing
and all that so there is more indians
outside of india today there is more
indian culture
alive in thailand and in myanmar
in indonesia and in cambodia than in
india itself so that situation would not
have been there if there was no invasion
of the mughals in the british
but it is what it is we need to evolve
again as a nation right now we are very
much
confused uh the system
kind of tries to make us ashamed of our
own culture
most of us like to tone it down even if
you practice our own religion or culture
at home
we don't show it in the open so these
things would not have been there
if the british and the and before the
the turks had not invaded
so that's the answer sir
what would happen if all the governors
of this country were replaced by
experience ias and ips
the iis and ips are the bureaucracy and
they are part of the problem
india needs people india needs to
overhaul its entire system
the nethers are a problem but the iis
and ips are also
many of them are good i'm not saying
they're all bad many of them really want
to serve the country
many of us many of them get into the ias
and ips because they want to give
something to the country
they want to contribute something but
the system forces them to behave in a
certain manner they have to take
orders from the politicians and the
politicians their entire
the system is such that they don't get
into politics to serve the country
they get into politics to serve
themselves the such is the system of
democracy in this country today
you must be asking yourself why do we
always have the same old
people who stand for election why don't
we have new people
it's because new people can't stand for
election
in this system you can technically send
for election but you will get nowhere
because if you want to have a chance in
the electoral system in india
you need to be able to spend crores of
rupees in the election campaign
if you don't do that you are invisible
and
in a democracy everybody should have the
right to vote in the right to stand for
election on
a level field and that isn't there in
india so it's
it's a democracy only name people should
be
able to stand for election on the same
equal
level footing as anybody else and only
the politicians have that privilege
today because of the
power of money and that's why political
parties are so powerful
and that's why and the thing is that in
political parties you don't have
internal democracy
right there are no elections within
political parties these are all
monolithic fiefdoms it's always the same
people in power
and sometimes if they're not in power
then they will
choose who will come to power you know
as a king maker so these are some of the
internal problems in our so-called
democratic system
and that's why the country is in the
shape it is today that's why it's been
put in all kinds of different directions
everybody has small local petty personal
agendas
to to enhance their power and their
money
and they basically don't care about the
country there are very few politicians
who actually care about the country i'm
not saying none of them does
some of them do have integrity and they
do want to do something good for the
country
but those are in a minority as we all
know very well
so these are the systemic structural
issues within the indian
system the so-called democratic system
which we have
adopted wholesale from a small island
west of europe this system is not
appropriate for an enormous
subcontinent sized country as
india this system that we have adopted
this westminster democracy system
it evolved over several centuries in a
small little island
which was not really a democracy it was
actually a monarchy
so this system is entirely inappropriate
for india india it
needs to have its own democratic system
democracy with indian characteristics we
have that before
the invasions india was india is the
birthplace of democracy not greece
the greek democracy is a sham the
ancient greek democracy
it was a sham so that's what we need to
learn from our history we had our own
democratic system during the
mahajanapadas and even before that
so we can learn something from that and
we can try and revert back to
an indigenous democratic system i am a
firm believer in democracy
the people come first the people are the
highest
in a nation the highest morality for a
ruler is that the nation and its people
must prosper so we need that sort of
democracy
not the nato should prosper or the
bureaucrats should prosper
which is what's happening right now so
there is definitely
a great deal of scope for change and
reform but right now
every politician is invested in the
system that brought them to power
that's why we are stuck with this system
that was started 70 years ago
and it's still going on the people who
created the system are all dead
and we are having to deal with it we
should have the power
to change the system and to ameliorate
it to make it better
in order to make this country more
efficient and to
start fulfilling the enormous potential
that india has
so changes are needed reforms are needed
when they will happen i have no idea
this should happen soon
when were the vedas written well we
don't exactly know when they were
written it was a very long time ago
see the rig veda speaks about a time
when
india was a rural civilization
it there is no mention of cities of
a great urban uh civilization or culture
it's all about the pastoral life the
rural life
so it is clearly something that greatly
predates
the so-called harappan phase of our
civilization
the harappan phase of our civilization
was a massively
industrialized and urbanized society
every town every village was properly
planned it was well made
you had multi-storage buildings you had
incredible
engineering feats for that time you had
great architecture
everything was standardized weights
measures everything so this was a highly
evolved society it had evolved over
thousands of years
the vedas talk about the time much
before that
so the harappan phase the mature urban
phases around 3000 bce
or thereabouts here and the early
harappan phase is about five or six
thousand bce
maybe seven thousand bce so maybe
that could be perhaps the time
when the vedas were written or maybe
somewhat before that
so these and and from the age of the
saraswati also
we can get some clue of when the vedas
were written
because the rigveda speaks about the
saraswati as this mighty
powerful river the greatest of all
rivers in the country
and that happened at least before
6000 bce because around 6000 bce the
indian monsoon started declining
and the saraswati started declining
herself and she died out
around 1500 bce of the rebounds so the
rig weather speaks about a river which
was in its prime not a river in decline
so that is at least 6000 bc which is 8
000 years before today
so all of this evidence although it is
circumstantial
all of it when we take it together it
looks like the is at least 8 000 years
old
or if not older so that is
the information we have as of today
beyond that we can't say for sure but i
think
from this information that i just gave
you it's at least
8 000 years old
is it fine to say that millions of
people died
during 1940 to 50 because of gandhi
alone and the bad decisions he took
well gandhi did not kill anybody we know
that he believed in non-violence
fasting all that but the bad decisions
he took well
he did not speak against the british
okay what this what other decision could
he have taken
let's go back to the time mr gandhi came
back to india
late 1910s late night when did gandhi
come back to india from south africa
let me look up the exact date when did
gandhi
return to india
okay he came back in 1915. see the thing
about history is you don't have to
memorize every date
if you try and memorize dates you will
lose track of the cause and equa
cause and effect uh change the real
deal about learning history is to
understand causality the cause and
effect
chain dates you can always look up
everything is available online
you don't have to memorize dates so
gandhi came back to india in 1915 and
very quickly he established himself
miraculously
as the greatest and most powerful leader
in the indian national congress
which was created by the british okay
the british created the indian national
congress it was
in a vehicle of the british
so this guy comes back to india 1915
in in just a couple of years he's become
all powerful
he has sidelined all the leaders of the
congress people like jinnah
are disillusioned jinnah was an indian
nationalist fyi
you know he was completely marginalized
by gandhi all other
leaders were sidelined gandhi became the
shining star almost overnight
how did that happen strange isn't it and
by 1920 he was regarded as the
tallest leader in the country everyone
worshipped him
everyone basically undulated him
and they would do anything he said so
what if gandhi had
issued a proclamation in 1920
kill all the british go outside
go out on the street find one british
person find one
british occupier of our land and kill
him you kill one person you go home
that's it your job is done
if he had issued that order to the
people of india
british rule would have been oh would
have been over in 28 to 14 hours
and millions and millions of lives would
have been saved
the lives that they killed by the lives
they took by
engineering famine after famine because
there were many more famines
after 1920 that that are not even
properly recorded
right and it's not just famines people
died in famines those numbers are
under reported the british figures but
also
there were lots of debts because of
malnutrition from families yes we know
but also because of epidemics because
when you are malnourished you are more
vulnerable to illnesses
and those deaths from this terrible
epidemics of plague and what not
these were reportedly not recorded as
part of the families
so the actual figures are much worse
than what we are
told so had gandhi issued the order to
the people of india go kill the british
and british rule
the british were how many in number 100
000 or so in india
and india had 300 million people they
would have wiped the british out
in a just war in 24 to 48 hours
it is perfectly justifiable to kill
your oppressors and to kill foreign
occupiers of your land
it is perfectly valid there is no
hindsight needed in that you
ahinsa is also basically preventing
long-term violence to kill the oppressor
and prevent long-term violence
is also a hinza so gandhi gave us a
perverted
warped definition of ahinsa he said
inaction is ahinsa which is absolutely
wrong
and and basically he prolonged
british rule in india for at least two
to three decades
had he as the indian leader tallest
indian leader
actually issued the call for violence
against the british
there was no way the british would have
lasted beyond 24 to 48 hours
so he had the the power to do that but
he chose to prolong
british rule and to delay india's
independence by
at least two decades so yes you are
right that millions of people died
because of the
decisions mr gandhi took or did not take
it is time we reevaluate the role
of mohammed az gandhi in our country's
history
okay some more questions
roman asks what are my views on a stupa
located in nala mumbai and the artifacts
found
during the 1880s there is not much data
on the internet
there are stupas everywhere in this
country
there are artifacts everywhere in this
country and they are not recorded they
are not
there is no documentation was once
known as sopara surprise
in old days i believe it was a very
major
uh center of of trade
and learning uh during what
during the time of the king the great
chakra pakistan
etc who who no one knows about today
those are very great kings
uh so yes it is these are these are very
significant uh archaeological finds and
unfortunately they are not documented
at the asi like i spoke about in a
previous episode
they have no inclination towards uh
towards preserving
our real heritage they are only
interested in preserving our the
heritage of our occupiers which
is unfortunate so yeah there is a stupa
in alaska
it is not excavated it is just a big
mound i think covered with earth the
most part
and there are thousands or tens of
thousands of such archaeological sites
throughout india
many of them will be incredibly valuable
they will have all kinds of
incredible artifacts if we find them we
will actually be able to piece together
the real history of this country
in way more detail than we know today
our understanding of our history
before the foreign turkic invasion is is
quite vague right
so there's so much left to discover and
unfortunately nothing is being done
right now
hopefully hopefully it will be done in
the future
but yes you are right there is this
stupa in alaska
still unexcavated unexplored and maybe
it's a good thing because of the asmr
have to find priceless
artifacts there those will disappear who
knows
there is a strange pattern of such
things happening
so that's about the stupa in sophara
mumbai north mumbai
okay i have answered that question about
the questions are in them
when british the british first set up
factories in india and gained immense
profits why didn't indians learn those
kills
and set up their own factories with the
british had little to no power
the factories they set up in india were
basic factories india was an
industrialized nation an industrialized
civilization
before the british came to india indian
skills
india had factories india was a fully
urbanized
fully industrialized culture the british
de-industrialized india they destroyed
those industries
there were so many industries textiles
ship making
uh irons melting india made the best
steel in the history of the world
it was called wood steel but the british
was called damascus steel
but the arabs but it was indian steel it
was made in india
it was just brought to damascus in the
raw form and then it was it was forged
into swords and whatever
other uh implements so india
developed this this uh technology it's
an incredibly
advanced technology around 500 bce of
thereabouts
it was called in southern india
it was developed i believe in tamilnadu
and
later on in sri lanka also you find
evidence of that so india had all these
industries in
all different technological domains
which were destroyed by the british
because they wanted indians to buy
british goods
so to do that they had to first destroy
indian industries
so the british de-industrialized india
india
is the original industrialized nation
and civilization
so there was nothing great to gain from
those pathetic little skills the british
were
imparting in those factories it was all
basic skills
we already had much higher skills which
were destroyed
so that's that's the actual answer
okay yeah this is a question i that
turns up all the time is gobleck
older than our civilization see go back
is a single site single archaeological
site
it may be a remnant of our larger
culture we don't know
there are a couple of other sites around
it in that region in
anatolia but it's not a civilization
a civilization is something else a
civilization is
a large geographical area in which you
have a single
overarching culture a single unifying
language
and you have a society whose
institutions
are all based in the indigenous culture
they are
the foundational principles and morals
and ethics of every institution
and of the laws are within the
indigenous culture
so that's what a civilization is it's
something that has
which is a net exporter of culture and
something that has a very large area of
influence it
far exceeds its boundaries that's a
civilization that's what india was
governed is one archaeological site
so it's not a civilization first of all
is it older than indian civilization
well it seems to be about 11 000 years
old which would make it older
than the oldest uh archaeological site
we find in india which is
piranha which is about nine and a half
or ten thousand years old
so as of today yes it seems to be older
than the oldest archaeological site we
have
excavated thus far but we know that
there are
several thousand harappan era
archaeological sites
in the super sundu region that have
never been excavated
we have excavated and explored less than
one percent
of the actual number of sites that we
have so the moment we start excavating
and exploring more
the real antiquity of our civilization
will start emerging
and i have no doubt that it's gonna go
back fifteen thousand years or even
twenty thousand years
so with the data that we have today yes
it is older than our oldest
archaeological site
in the future we may find different
evidence
okay some more some more some more
questions
okay i'm getting so many questions i'm
getting lost in that
the harappans were regulated people most
they were most likely post rigvedic
people but yeah okay they were vedic
they were part of the vedic continuum
yes but while sanskrit is written and
read from left to right
why was the discord script written from
right left very good question i love it
these are the kind of questions we
should be asking only then can we
understand
history and our past properly great
question brilliant question sir
sanskrit is a language
a script is a vehicle that carries the
language
sanskrit is so old it has been
carried on a number of scripts you have
the
script you have the brahma script you
have the script
today you have the deva nagar script you
can even use other scripts
for sanskrit right it is so
old it has been it has been uh written
in a variety
of scripts you can even use the tibetan
script to
write sanskrit which you will find some
in some places in
north of the himalayas you can even use
the mongolian soyambhu script to write
sanskrit
so the point is that sanskrit is such an
ancient language
it has been written in different scripts
in different periods of time
so today that they've not got a script
is written written in a certain manner
from right to left or sorry from left to
right
in the past i think it was karoshi if i
am not mistaken
which was written the other way around
which is fine
so it is because of the incredible
antiquity of this language
which has been around for several
thousand years for many thousand years
that's why you find it written in a
variety of scripts
at different periods in time and there
is no rule or law that says that
sanskrit
can only be written in a certain manner
it can be written in any way
as long as the script is logical and it
is able to
carry this sanskrit language properly
and it's able to
reproduce the pronunciations accurately
that's all that matters
so during the vedic age there may have
been a different script
that we are not aware of today right
during the harappan era also there could
have been
that could have been a different script
like we know
so that's the thing uh
i hope that answers your question
why doesn't india patent yoga well india
doesn't seem to be interested in uh
in preserving its culture today you find
that yoga is being uh
it's being distorted in the west there's
all kinds of weird forms of yoga
goat yoga and dog yoga and hot yoga and
cold yoga
and drunk yoga and whatnot
it's it's been reduced to a form of
exercise a form of stretching power yoga
and all that and india is doing nothing
to preserve
the sanctity
and and the basic uh
the original form of what yoga is india
has
basically given up on yoga it looks like
and who's the
authority in india that is in charge of
preserving our culture it's the
government of india
so here's what i say should be done see
let me give you a different example you
have something called shaolin kung fu
now shaolin kung fu is also practiced in
the west
but they don't deviate from the
classical
school of shaolin kung fu they don't
start implementing uh
or introducing uh new variations or
forms
of into this ancient practice into
the into this ancient martial art
because and the reason for this is
because
the final authority in shaolin kung fu
is the shaolin temple in henan province
of china
the shaolin temple is the global
authority of what is
what is the correct form of kung fu and
what is not
so in india we don't have any such
institution that decides what yoga is
and what yoga is not
so india should create an institution
an authority that will be the final
authority in yoga
it will it will adjudicate the matter of
what constitutes yoga and what does not
it will lay down strict guidelines
and principles and any form of yoga in
the west
that does not adhere to these principles
will be declared as
not being is not being considered yoga
so that
is a simple thing india can do an
institution
of yoga maybe uh an institute of yoga
which is the final global authority just
like
shaolin the shaolin temple is for kung
fu
it's a simple step india can take and
reclaim
yoga and sanctity of yoga i mean
it doesn't cost much to do this it just
takes a little bit of leadership
so unfortunately india is currently not
interested in in
pursuing its national interest when it
comes to indian culture indian culture
is being mangled and distorted worldwide
it's being appropriated now many people
the west are even
beginning to claim that yoga is is not
even indian it was something that the
british introduced in india
and so on which is absolutely a lie we
know that
so it's not about patenting yoga it's
about creating
a globe an institution an institute of
yoga which is the global authority
india the government of india should
create this institution this institute
and declare it the global authority
in the uk in adjudicating matters of
yoga and deciding what constitutes yoga
and what does not
considered yoga that way india will be
able to reclaim
yoga for itself because india is the
birthplace of yoga
india is the nation the culture the
civilization that gave this great art
form
this great practice
to the world it's a gift of india so
india needs to reclaim that
in this manner easy easy to do
i hope it's done
okay some more interesting questions
oh is it okay this is by garuda is it
true that we have some 40 million
manuscripts out of which 95
are not translated bb roy made this
claim
uh it is known for a fact that we have
several
million ancient manuscripts mostly palm
leaf manuscripts
and parchments of various kinds that
are gathering dust in various places
some of them are in the hands of the asi
some of them are gathering dust in
various temples in india ancient temples
they have mostly in the south of india
which escaped
destruction during the turkic
depredations of india
so yes there are millions of manuscripts
that are just lying around
gathering dust they are crumbling they
are beginning to crumble many of them
and if nothing is done we will lose all
the information that is contained in
them
many of them are really ancient ones
they don't even know
we will not know how old they are unless
they are catalogued and tested
so none of that is happening as of today
so yes
we have a great wealth of information
waiting
to be tapped into and preserved
very old manuscripts which
basically contain a great deal of
historical records of our past
so most of them are not translated i
don't want them to be translated just
preserve them in the digital in the
digital form even in the original sense
that is fine
or tamil or whatever language they are
written in they need to be digitized
that is the first step we don't need
everything to be translated into english
let's learn sanskrit and read this
manuscript right why not
so the first the most essential step is
to digitize the memory
the manuscripts so that they don't get
lost if they crumble
which they eventually will so
that's the situation that is most likely
correct i think it's more than 95 not
translated maybe 98
so that's the situation we are in right
now
okay what is india doing to counter
china's string of pearls initiative
uh good question uh we do have some very
good uh
uh geographical natural geographical
gifts we have the andaman islands which
are like
a natural unsinkable aircraft carrier
so i think the government of india has
constructed a couple of airstrips there
so we can land uh military planes there
fighter planes
and transport planes and all that uh
india is building a few submarines maybe
five or six
scorpion submarines and india is
investing in nuclear submarine
technology so we will have a fleet of
nuclear submarines will be five or six
of them in the next 20 years
so india is doing a little bit some baby
steps to counter this thing what can
india do
it can do much more it can develop a
blue water navy that can actually
take control of the indian ocean region
just to safeguard it from
from the kind of actions that china is
known to take
right so there is some steps are being
taken we have military satellites that
coordinate our navy together
and give it a real-time view of what's
happening you know
network centric uh
network-centric warfare if required so
some steps are being taken i would like
to see many more steps being taken
india has the potential to basically uh
safeguard the indian ocean region for
all civilized countries if it so chooses
to and for itself
it is in the in india's national
interest to develop a powerful
blue water navy because if you are not
powerful somebody else will come and
replace you as a power nature abhors
a vacuum power also above the vacuum
right now the indian ocean region is
kind of a power vacuum
there is some american presence there
some french presence a
tiny bit of indian presence and there is
an increasing chinese presence
in the indian ocean region so the
chinese are intent
on filling this power vacuum india
should not let that happen
and the string of pearls initiative is
essentially this port that china is
constructing everywhere
so there are ports in myanmar ports in
bangladesh port in sri lanka
maldives also is a target and pakistan
as we know
so the solution is a powerful blue water
navy
that can take out a chinese port at will
at any given time if required so that's
what india should do
india should invest in submarines india
should invest in surface
above surface vessels india should
invest in
proper distributed lethality in the
indian ocean
so i hope that it is something that is
on the planning board and something that
will be implemented soon because
because in 10 years time things will be
very different india needs to quickly
adapt and evolve with the
winds of geopolitical change that we are
witnessing right now it's going in a
certain direction
the united states is waning as a power
china is rising as a power
and if it continues like this then india
will be in a very dangerous neighborhood
so it is time for india to quickly take
action
and become a power in its own right
so that the chinese are properly counter
balanced and they behave themselves
good question sir
good question uh one word one people is
that the principle of communism
how does communism differ from socialism
one world one people means a
mono culture it means that every culture
every local manifestation of any culture
has been stamped out and there is only
one ruling principle in the world
communism marxism that is
what one world one people means we are
not one world one people
we are a lot of different people who
should live in harmony
we should have local cultures we should
promote
localism that's what makes the world
beautiful that's what is so interesting
when you travel
you see different cultures everywhere
you go it that's what makes the world
interesting
if you have just one culture everywhere
good god
i mean that's the that's the worst
nightmare right
so what exactly is communism right
i have said this in the past i'm gonna
say it again communism
here's the one sentence definition of
communism
communism is a socio-political toolkit
and when i say communism i also mean
marxism marxism communism social
socialism these are more or less
interchangeable
socialism is a softer form of marxism or
communism
so let's talk about marxism in one
sentence
marxism is a socio-political toolkit
whose
sole objective is to enable a very small
group of people
to capture and retain political power at
any
cost by any means that's what it is
so everything you are taught about
communism is to reduce you to current
foreigner
to reduce you to pawns on the chessboard
that this small group of people
will use to maximize that power that's
what it is
communism differs from socialism
socialism is a softer form of communism
uh socialism does envisage some form of
democracy india is officially
socialistic
a socialist secular republic
socialism is basically the pursuit of
poverty everybody should be on the same
level financially
no matter how talented you are you may
be you will be dragged down to the same
level as the average
that's essentially what socialism is it
is not the right ideology or
our system for anybody to follow uh
and neither is capitalism capitalism is
the unbridled
pursuit of never-ending
money of never-ending resources on a
finite planet it's going to destroy the
planet which already
is so neither capitalism is the right
solution neither is communism nor
neither is marxism
neither is socialism the world needs a
different solution to its problems
so i am not a believer believer in
socialism
or communism or marxism and even
capitalism is very dangerous
because it's destroying the planet we
need a balance
in things so a different solution
is required for the world's problems
okay
some more interesting questions i'm sure
there are lots
[Music]
we don't know we don't have sufficient
information
we don't have sufficient data there is
clearly something
about the taj mahal that is hidden from
the people
there is a passage under the structure
which leads someone else and it is
possible it could have been
a pre turkic structure
in the past we don't know for sure the
asi
is in possession of this monument and it
doesn't allow any any investigation into
the matter
so right now i would say that the
possibility is there
it is possible that it could have been
something different that something else
existed on that location
before the so-called taj mahal was
constructed maybe it was
a pre-turkish structure there that
has uh been destroyed and that and whose
records we have lost so we will know
only if there is a proper archaeological
investigation
the esi doesn't want that to happen in
the future if we disband the asin
and replace it with a proper
professional archaeological
organization that maybe we will be able
to find to shed some light on this
matter
as of today we have insufficient data to
answer this question
okay more questions
my views about chanakya's economic
policies and whether they can be
implemented successfully today in our
country
well those policies that we implemented
he did them very successfully
two and uh two thousand few few hundred
years ago two thousand three hundred
years
or so ago so the world was very
different then
today's world is different we can
certainly take a great deal of
inspiration
from chanakya's policies economic
policies other policies
and we can modify them and
tailor them to suit today's
situation today's world today's world is
very different we have
a different pace of life we have
technology different technology
and we have a different geopolitical
climate so everything is different but
the principles of the national interest
still
apply they always apply and that's what
guided vishnu gupta
so the policies he followed were based
on that
on the principle of the national
interest and those policies were very
successful
in india those were indigenous policies
tailor-made for india's
civilization and culture so we can
definitely
take inspiration from that and we can
study those policies in detail and maybe
tweak them
modify them to be implemented
in today's uh today's india i think it
should be very very much possible if we
change it
and adapt it to the present 21st century
climate
why are we thought that gandhiji gave us
freedom uh subhash bhabu bhagat singh
sarwakar or real gems of indian freedom
then why are there no mentions of
subhash bhabhi disrespect of sovereignty
why because the ncert and other textbook
writers had a very
clear political agenda they were under
instructions by the ruling regime of
india
the nehru regime to glorify nehru and
his benefactor mr mohandas gandhi
so they kept on writing the entire
curriculum of indian history is slanted
in this ideological
fashion even if you look at the master's
degree
uh textbooks that you find in various
indian universities
bhagat singh is referred to as an
extremist
and a terrorist so this is the kind of
uh twisting of facts that has been done
he was a freedom fighter
he fought for the freedom of india he
died for the freedom of india
he gave up his life for the country
and so what if we did it by violent
means gandhi's non-violence
delayed our independence by at least 20
years had we resorted to
justifiable violence against the british
we would have been free in 48 hours if
the entirety of india
went out in the streets to wipe the
british out it was that easy for us to
do it
it is because of the kind of leaders we
had that we suffered so much
a nation's destiny depends on the kind
of leaders
we have it's all about leadership it's
all about leadership
today tomorrow in the past it's always
been about leadership
if you have the wrong leader you're
gonna go in the wrong direction
so that's what happened after gandhi it
was nehru mr
the great mr shree neroji who
ensured that our textbooks go in a
certain direction ideologically
the education system has been used as an
instrument of
of social engineering it has been used
to brainwash generations of india
indians into believing the wrong things
and
the leftists the marxists of india were
given
the charge of writing india's history
textbooks and that's why
we have we are in the situation that we
are today
the mr uh booze so much in the most
vital
is completely marginalized there is very
little
written about him compared to how much
i mean how significant he was and like
you said other
other freedom fighters are disrespected
or not mentioned at all
so this is all because of the naruto
regime and the later regimes
which continued in that direction so i'm
glad that today we are all discussing
this openly
i'm glad that today's youngsters are all
beginning to become aware
of these distortions and i think
going forward we will know more modern
history in a more accurate fashion
so i'm really happy about this
right
okay poco chan is the modern autumn
atomic model accurate is it possible
that the current atomic model may be
wrong
see uh the best model that we have as of
today
is called the standard model so that is
a
family of particles i think it's 17
subatomic particles
in various counterparts and
anti-particles and all that
that is the best model we have thus far
uh and the quantum field theory is the
most
accurate theory that we have
as of today now we know that it
this this model this entire framework
does not include
gravity the force of gravity and we
don't
know much about the force of gravity so
clearly it is not the most accurate
model but it's the most accurate we have
thus far
it is not entirely accurate it cannot
account for gravitation
it cannot account for dark matter and
dark energy which is 95
of the universe's mass energy so
to the extent that we see the world it
seems to be accurate but there's a whole
unseen universe out there
which immensely dwarfs what we can see
so as far as that is concerned we have
no idea what it is
so our modern model the standard model
is accurate to about five percent of the
universe
so that's the situation we are in right
now okay but it's the best we have
hopefully some new breakthroughs will
happen soon in
theoretical physics
i don't know many people claim they have
seen ashwa
master of the son of chary who was
cursed in the mahabharata bashari
krishna
to be alive with pain till the end of
kalyuga is he still alive well i haven't
seen him
and to the best of our knowledge
immortality doesn't exist
maybe it may have existed in a different
yogurt maybe our science isn't
completely accurate
but to the best of our knowledge we have
no credible evidence
of this and i haven't seen him i haven't
met anybody who has seen him
there is no documentary evidence that
ashford is alive
no photographs no video so
like i said we don't have sufficient
evidence to say that he is still alive
he may be possibly i'm not ruling out
the possibility
a small very small possibility but to
the best of our
of our knowledge this may not be true
it may be possibly
okay some more questions
is democracy good for a developing
country like india that's the age-old
question isn't it
i believe that subhash chandra bose had
intended
to impose a dictatorship for about 20
years
until india developed properly
i am a firm believer in democracy yes
but sometimes
the democracy is not right the kind of
democracy i mean democracy takes many
forms
and the form of democracy the so-called
democracy we have today
is not suitable for our country it
doesn't take our country forward it just
holds it back
it doesn't give people the power
democracy is supposed to empower people
it doesn't empower the people
the people are still supplicants to the
politicians and the bureaucrats
so the kind of democracy we have today
is not good for a developing country
like india
india needs to develop a democracy that
truly
empowers the people and not the small
minority the leaders the nethers the
politicians
the people must be empowered and
if that happens then it's good for india
in some cases people believe a
dictatorship is good like i just
mentioned
for example in singapore singapore was a
dictatorship for a very long time under
mr lee kuan yew
he was what's called a benevolent
dictator he actually did
all his life he spent trying to develop
the country and make
them making his small city state more
powerful and
more prosperous and he was not
oppressive
like some other dictators that we know
of
so so yeah he is called a benevolent
dictator
so such such a thing may possibly have
been good for india in the first 20 or
so years
somebody likes watching the remotes
possibly that's all hypothetical we
don't know
but i definitely am of the opinion that
our democracy needs to change
it needs to empower the people and not
live
leave people at the mercy of the the
politicians and the
institutions that don't really serve the
country so that's
the direction india should take a better
democracy
a democracy that truly empowers the
people
that's what's needed
okay i'm gonna take let's say two more
questions
two more questions
okay sumaid asks shouldn't we ban the
communist ideology and parties in india
given their bloody history and
separatist stance
during india's partition i am of the
firm opinion
that the national interest has to come
first
a democracy cannot allow the kind of
freedom of speech in which you
speak against the country and its
interests and you actually promote the
interests of your enemies
and any political ideology that promotes
the interests of
outside forces over your own national
interest
cannot be allowed in a democracy but
that's the kind of democracy we have
in the in the name of freedom of speech
and in the name of democracy
anti-nationalism open anti-nationalism
is allowed whether in the form of speech
or even worse in the form of
international activities
in the form of demand in the name of
democracy i believe that that sort of
democracy doesn't
serve the nation democracy has only one
function
its function is to serve the nation laws
have only one function
they are supposed to serve the nation
the constitution has only one function
it's to serve the nation the moment it
stops serving the nation it has to be
changed
it has to be adapted to this to the new
circumstances
and we cannot keep on worshiping a set
of laws that were written by the british
and the constitution that was written by
an unelected body
right so things need to change
communism is anti-national anywhere in
the world whether it's in the us or in
india
communism is not a force for good we
cannot allow
such ideologies bloodthirsty ideologies
in the name of democracy yes i i think
that what you are saying
does have a great deal of merit to it i
agree with you
all right one more question my friends
and then we are done for today
saurabh asks why was mr
jinnah against the killah movement and
partition of bengal
on the basis of religion even though he
fueled the creation of part of pakistan
that is a great question i mean why
doesn't this
is why isn't this addressed in our
history textbooks
mr muhammad ali jinnah was a true
secularist
he was not a practicing muslim he drank
alcohol he
ate pork right he was a true secularist
he was a proponent of hindu muslim
brotherhood
hindu muslim unity he was of the belief
that hindus and muslims should
work together and live in harmony and
keep their
so-called religious differences aside
for the for the sake of the nation
he was an indian nationalist mr jinnah
in the early 20th century
and he opposed the creation the
formation of the muslim league which he
would later join
strangely enough when the muslim league
was formed he opposed its formation
he opposed gandhi's advocacy of the
khilafah movement
he opposed the partition of bengal
so this is the early career of muhammad
ali
he was a true indian nationalist and
then what happened
was that he was completely marginalized
by mr mohandas gandhi
mr gandhi was way more charismatic
than mohammed jinnah did not have a
pleasing personality
he was a very serious person he was not
pleasant to be with that's the kind of
person he was that's the kind of
personality here gandhi was very
pleasing
he was very inspiring so gandhi took
over
this entire independence movement
sidelined jinnah
jinnah was marginalized he eventually
joined the muslim league just to keep
his political career
alive he spent a number of years in
exile out of india out of politics
in the uk he was a very big anglophile
even though he was an indian nationalist
you know so that's the kind of
conflicted
personality mr jinnah had and he was
he spent a great deal almost a decade or
more slightly more in the wilderness the
uk out of politics
and then a transformation happened in
him he
chose to put self before nation
and he chose to serve
a small section of india rather than the
entirety of india which
was his true nature and that's why he
started
he went back and to india he joined the
muslim league and he started advocating
the creation of a separate nation for
the muslims
on the basis of the so-called two nation
theory
so that's how he changed sometime in the
1930s
he he took a complete u-turn and he
chose to put
self before nation so it's a sad
story it's a sad story of how somebody
changes so much because
of external circumstances and he ended
up destroying his own country
he ended up destroying the country that
he fought so much for
in the early stage of his career and
such is his
failure such as mohammed al-jannah's
failure that none of his descendants
has made pakistan their home all of his
descendants today
live in india that's how the cookie
crumbles
okay people thank you so much for your
questions we are done for today
uh great questions and we will continue
with a different topic tomorrow
tomorrow's world history
so i will see you tomorrow 9 00 pm
indian time until then take care
and